Which has saved countless lives in upland Britain - the Mountain Rescue Service.
Welcome to Countryfile from where it all started.
The village of Coniston sits at the north-west tip of Coniston Water in the south of the Lake District.
This is, without doubt, one of the most beautiful places in the entire world, challenging for both walkers and climbers.
But the mountainous terrain and the unpredictable weather conditions also make it one of the most dangerous, which is why Britain's first Mountain Rescue Service started life right here.
More about that in a moment.
Also on today's Countryfile, are we protecting the natural environment at the expense of our energy needs?
We've been sitting on our hands for too long talking and not making decisions.
And in many cases, the environment has intruded and stopped some developments taking place.
Why horses are paying the price of the Credit Crunch.
When I got him 17 years ago, I never imagined I'd be in a situation where I can't afford to keep him.
And Charlotte is learning to love kippers.
And it's just full of omega 3.
So, although you may think I'm acting like a pig, wolfing this down, I'm just doing it cos it's good for me!
For centuries, people have walked and climbed in the mountains.
But until the 1930s, if they got into trouble, there was no kind of rescue service to go to their help.
If they were lucky, they'd be spotted by other people out on the hills.
And if they couldn't move, they'd be carried down using, perhaps, an old gate like this, as an improvised stretcher.
Then, in 1933, a group of keen walkers and climbers set up the Joint Stretcher Committee to develop a lightweight stretcher that could be used on mountain rescues.
But the big breakthrough came after the Second World War, when permanent rescue teams were set up in Britain's mountain areas.
And the very first of them was here in Coniston.
That was in 1947 and now there are more than 50 mountain rescue groups around the country, each can draw on around 40 volunteers.
And one former Coniston member joined in 1950.
Well, we had a couple of stretchers, various splints, rope of course, a big first aid bag, a few storm lanterns.
That was about it.
We didn't even have proper footwear - we went in clogs.
And why do you think it was that Coniston had the first rescue team?
It came a real bad snow and all the quarrymen said, "We'd better go.
"We're going to get stuck up here."
So after they'd went, Jim Long said, "Oh, I've forgotten to knock that motor off."
And back he went to his motor.
The other guys waited and waited and waited and he never came.
Anyway, as they were searching, it was blanket, big snow drifts, and there's a chap just poking into a snowdrift, and he felt something soft.
Oh, he says, there's a sheep in here.
There wasn't - it was Jim.
And was he still alive?!
Yeah!
He was in a poor state but he got over it.
After that, they formed a body of men in case something like that happened again.
These days, the Coniston team is called out, on average, around 50 times a year.
And they're highly trained.
Well, here's something they'd have never dreamt of in the early days - a mountain rescue team with an indoor climbing wall!
What do you want this for when there's all those mountains outside?
Well, it allows us to give a fully structured, fully thought-out talk to a large number of people, describe and demonstrate the techniques.
When we've done that, we go out to the mountains and practise them.
Do you ever have any problem getting recruits?
Recently, we've had a really good influx of new members, really good people.
I suppose there are people who don't realise that this is a totally voluntary service?
That's the thing - we're part of the public service, but no, we're completely voluntary, completely self-funded.
Right, John, this is the control room where all the call-outs are run from.
This is where you're keeping in touch with the teams when they're out?
Yes, this radio here keeps in touch with the three mobiles and with the personal radios that all the guys carry themselves.
Here you've got a map of the whole of the southern Lake District.
Which is your patch?
Eh, from Windermere here up to Little Langdale in the north, and across to the Duddon over that side there.
That's a huge area.
Do you liaise with other mountain rescue teams?
You never quite know where somebody is, could be on anybody's area, so you get different teams covering a big area.
Ice axes, crampons, helmets and lamps are all part of the standard equipment for rescue teams But there's one item I didn't expect...
What on earth is this, then?!
That is for rescuing sheep...
Never!
..Off crags when they get crag-fast, yeah.
So it's not just humans you help, then?
No, not at all, not at all.
Even sheep.
And you get as for as you can to a rescue, then, in this?
Yeah.
Great piece of kit.
As you can see, there's been a lot of work.
And fully kitted out as an ambulance?
Yes, we can slide the stretcher straight into the back.
And how many of these have you got?
We've got three.
We've got one quite old one and then the two newer ones which we got sponsorship for.
Do you think, then, there's a case for some State funding?
I would prefer it didn't go that way.
Eh, it's hard work raising the money, but I think that's the way it should be.
Mountaineers helping mountaineers in trouble, really?
Yeah, exactly.
That's the way it's always been and it works.
I don't see any reason for changing it.
And at the end of the programme, we'll be seeing the Coniston team in action.
It's a sign of the times that the government has just created a new department for energy and climate change.
But balancing our need for power with the need to protect the environment is a huge challenge.
Here's Adam with this report.
We, as a society, need huge amounts of power.
We're also renowned for our passion for the natural world.
But is this desire to preserve the environment at all costs now threatening the very fabric of our society?
Some scientists say yes, they believe the desire from conservationists to protect everything from wildlife to the quality of our air, is in danger of causing an energy crisis where we won't be able to produce enough power to satisfy our needs.
The Government's admitted we need 30 gigawatts of new electricity capacity within two decades.
Critics say if that's going to happen, we need to up our game, even if it means sacrificing some natural habitats.
We've been sitting on our hands for too long talking and not making decisions.
And in many cases, the environment has intruded and stopped some developments taking place.
The answer is, we have to compromise.
And oddly enough, the environment is surprisingly resilient when it comes to change.
It's true environmental concerns are delaying or scuppering projects to provide power.
A giant wind farm proposal for the Isle of Lewis in Scotland was turned down partly because of fears birds would fly into the turbines.
When you're hitting birds in these numbers and densities, it is very difficult not to have a huge impact on them.
The idea of putting a barrage across the Severn Estuary has been delayed and delayed due to fears it'll damage the environment.
It will change for ever and completely the ecology of the Severn Estuary upstream of the barrage.
So we've got green lobbyists opposing green energy projects.
But by making the protection of wildlife our top priority, some, including European advisors like Professor Ian Fells, believe we're in danger of creating an energy crisis.
It's really rather a mess.
In fact, it's a worrying mess because, as you look into the future, it's unclear as to just what's gonna happen.
The mixture that we need is more renewables, the Severn Barrage is the best bet.
More nuclear power stations, but that will take time.
And we'll probably have to build more coal-fired stations, making them as clean as we possibly can.
Where does wildlife and the environment sit, in your view, when we need more energy?
Well, we have to compromise.
You can't stop a huge development because you're perhaps going to protect some rare species.
But what you don't do is stop some really important development, actually and in terms of something like the Severn Estuary - something like 5% of our energy from a renewable source.
You don't put that on one side cos you want to protect the dunlins.
That attitude has upset conservationists everywhere, including on the Moray Firth in Scotland where there are Government proposals to drill for oil and gas.
I've joined these volunteers who are monitoring 130 bottlenose dolphins.
There are concerns their habitat will be destroyed if the plans go ahead.
We've just come across a pod of dolphins and there's about 12 animals out there.
There's something very, very special about seeing them and you can understand why the people involved in this research project are so passionate about conserving and looking after the environment that they live in.
It is essential that we understand more about their populations, the status of their populations and in some cases, like with the bottlenose dolphin, where the population is 130 animals, an incredibly small, vulnerable population, then we would say yes, where there's a protected area like in the inner Moray Firth, the oil and gas industry shouldn't be allowed Some scientists say that they feel we could be facing serious energy crises and that we should be pragmatic about our wildlife and perhaps put them to one side.
I completely disagree with that.
I think, whilst we have to seriously consider the environment and weigh that up against the cost to energy, we can do both of those things together and apart from my own personal feelings, we have legal responsibilities to the marine environment and the species within it.
The Government hasn't made a final decision on drilling yet, but to these enthusiasts, it would be unthinkable.
Do you think that putting out oil rigs here would have an effect on these animals?
Oh, definitely.
Very definitely.
I mean, it's loud, drilling is loud and I don't want to think about oil spills at all... it's just not a very good idea to do it right here.
With the environment coming to the forefront on decisions about energy production, a whole new industry has sprung up in Britain.
Environmental consultancy now employs more than 170,000 people in the UK.
They help developers comply with EU legislation.
But some in the industry agree red tape can hold up key decisions.
In your world as a consultant, do you think there's sometimes too much consultation when it comes to energy projects, and that holds them up?
Undoubtedly so and with the energy situation, we are going to have to bring energy projects on-stream much quicker.
Where do you see the answer for our energy problems versus wildlife?
Well, wildlife will ultimately be most affected by climate change, so if we're going to tackle climate change, we've really got to grasp the mettle and take some difficult decisions if they have to be made.
On the other hand, I'm a great believer that you can protect local habitats and have renewable energy systems.
So I think with a bit of ingenuity and innovation, we can manage to hit both.
And perhaps concentrating on using less energy in conserving the wildlife that's threatened by our insatiable demand for more power.
These are an amazing part of Scotland's natural heritage, it would be a terrible shame to lose them.
Not just because of their intrinsic value, but cos of their value to the economy and to the people who come here as tourists to visit them and to have an encounter like we've just had.
The trouble is that once the lights start going out, then everything spirals down into despair and you can forget about climate change...
In fact, your economy goes, meaning you're not going to be able to help do anything about climate change.
So that comes first and climate change comes second.
Nature-lovers might be heartened to at least see environmental issues moving up the political agenda.
But clearly, we have some tough challenges ahead if we're to balance the need to protect our wildlife, reduce climate change and produce enough energy to satisfy our needs in the future.
The Lake District is a perfect place to come walking but so is the Offa's Dyke Path, which runs for 177 miles from Prestatyn in North Wales to Sedbury Cliffs on the Severn Estuary.
And unlike this place, it's a journey that takes in many different kinds of trees and one man has given up his day job to seek out every ancient tree there is along the route and this is his Video Diary.
Hi, I'm Rob McBride and I'm the tree-hunter and I'm walking Offa's Dyke today as part of the campaign by the Woodland Trust to find all the ancient trees in the countryside.
I'm near Trefonen and gonna visit some trees that have been reported on the dyke.
These are trees I've not seen before.
Being a tree-hunter involves going out and discovering these hidden gems that are out there in our countryside.
OK, this looks like one of the good trees on the dyke, highlighted by a local volunteer.
You have to try and get the narrowest place.
And sometimes it's a struggle!
So we're at 442...
4 metres 42, so it falls into, looking at the characteristics of the tree as well, a veteran tree.
A nice oak tree actually on the path of the dyke.
Judging by that tree there, I would say that's a definite ancient tree.
Different than what we've seen before - the smaller veteran trees.
That...is an ancient oak tree.
Wow!
How can you not be impressed by that?
That is amazing, isn't it?
Who needs artists when you've got nature's art there?
It's just...brilliant, isn't it?
That's a big one.
We've gotta measure that.
7...
16 - 7.16 metres!
This is a Henry VIII tree.
I think 500, perhaps.
Perhaps even a bit more.
But it was definitely around when Henry VIII was on the throne.
Lots and lots of the trees that we're finding have no protection.
And within ten minutes with a chainsaw, this 500 to 600-year-old tree, could be gone forever.
So, I'm on a new section of the dyke.
I've found 99 trees so far on the dyke and we're looking for the 100th tree.
Wow.
Something very interesting here.
Well this, perhaps, is a veteran rowan tree.
You can see by the angle of this tree, that it's pretty special anyway.
But I'm guessing it's over a metre in girth because I can't hook around it!
So that's over 1.5 metres.
For its species - again, it's not all about massive seven or ten-metre oak trees.
The other species - hawthorn and rowan, apple, crab apple...
So this is nearly 2 metres - this is 1.93.
So that's a recordable veteran tree for its species on the dyke.
And it's certainly on the dyke - coming right out of the dyke.
So I've come from Prestatyn all the way in the north and finding this brilliant, brilliant tree, just poking, horizontal nearly, out of the dyke, is a really good tree to end this section on.
Number 100!
Good tree - I like it.
And here's to many more.
Well, here in the Lake District, the weather has always had the reputation for suddenly turning treacherous.
And 200 years ago, in March 1808, the people of the small town of Grasmere heard news of a tragedy here on the mountains - a tragedy which still has its impact to this day.
George and Sarah Green, who were a couple, had a young family, who lived in Grasmere, decided they had business to go over to Langdale which meant going across the mountains, across Langdale Fell.
And on their way back, although the weather was closing in, they decided to make their way home.
Unfortunately, it was a very severe snow storm and they never returned home on that day of 19th March.
The children waited until the following morning to raise the alarm and then many people from the village went out onto the Langdale Fell to search for them.
George was found at the bottom of a steep crag, having fallen.
His wife Sarah was also found dead, obviously having sheltered under a bush during the snow storm.
So a terrible tragedy, then, for this village of Grasmere.
There were six children.
What happened to them?
Well, there was no provision for children at that time and so they could easily have been made destitute.
But the people in the village took them into their own homes and arranged for them to be in homes close to each other and a fund was set up on their behalf.
The tragedy of the Greens came to the attention of Lakeland's great poet, William Wordsworth, who lived here at Dove Cottage, which is now part of the Wordsworth Museum.
The countryside around Grasmere inspired much of his lyrical writing.
What happened to the Greens couldn't have been in sharper contrast.
The Wordsworth Museum currently has an exhibition telling the story of the tragedy.
And among its collection of books and letters is an original manuscript by the poet, detailing the sad events.
Wordsworth wrote a poem, didn't he, about the Greens.
Did he know the family?
Yes, he knew the family.
Their daughter, Sally Green, was the servant to them in Dove Cottage.
So it meant that when the parents died, it was very touching, very personal to them.
This is a letter that Wordsworth wrote to his friend and fellow poet, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, just after the tragedy.
And in the letter, he includes the poem that you mentioned.
Oh, here...
"Who weeps for strangers?
Many wept for George and Sarah Green "Wept for that pair's unhappy end Whose grave may here be seen..."
It's a long poem, isn't it - many verses.
Why did he write it?
He wrote it, as he said in the letter to Coleridge, for Coleridge to do anything he could with it.
He said he could recite it, he could circulate it, publish it.
He could use Wordsworth's name or not use it - anything that he thought could be done to raise money for the children, he wished Coleridge to do.
'London society responded to the poem, 'sending money for the children of this poor and lowly couple 'who'd died in the snow.'
And do you think what happened all those years ago, has any relevance to this village today?
Yes, I think it has because it's a very tight-knit community and one which welcomes new people in and welcomes millions of visitors each year.
But at its heart, we still support one another, we still encourage one another and there's a still a fantastic community life here in this village.
Well, this is Coniston Water, one of the large expanses of water that make the Lake District so special.
And another part of the UK renowned for its watery beauty is the west coast of Scotland.
And a little while ago, Ben went there to explore the Isle of Skye.
'Skye is the largest of the Inner Hebrides.
'It has 350 miles of coastline.
'And you're never more than five miles from the sea, 'which is exactly where my Skye adventure begins.
'I'm sea-kayaking with Gordon Brown, who runs courses here on Skye 'and is one of the country's top instructors.'
This is beautiful.
It's a tough job you have, Gordon(!)
It is, yeah, definitely!
'It's a more gentle pursuit than you'd think, 'so it's no surprise that interest in the sport in booming.'
How often are you out on the water?
Pretty much every day.
Really?
I'm curious, what sort of age group comes out?
I'm assuming it's mainly younger people?
When we started the business here, it was very much younger people and thrill-seekers.
But now it's changing and we're looking more at people who are in their 50s - kids left school and university and left home.
Shall we keep wandering...
Absolutely, yeah.
Let's go.
It's very rare that I'm actually speechless cos somewhere is so beautiful, but I had no idea that this was hidden here on Skye!
It is, definitely, it's a stunning, stunning place.
What a fantastic way of exploring Skye!
And what a backdrop!
'Alan Campbell is a photographer who left Glasgow 'six years ago to live and work here on Skye.'
Hi, Alan!
Hi there, Ben.
I've been told that you're the man to come and see if I want to take beautiful landscape photographs here on Skye?
How are you?
Very well.
My first question is that obviously you're spoilt for choice here, everywhere I look there seems to be something amazing to look at and take a picture of.
How do you find your inspiration then?
Very nice saying, that's a beautiful mountain, that's a beautiful tree, a wonderful beach, whatever.
But it's a little bit more about being a bit more critical about what you can see there and honing in to the specifics of what it is that makes a mountain beautiful, or tree fantastic, or beach wonderful.
And trying to almost simplify the view down to its basic elements that represents what that means to you.
'Meet Pebbles and Tay - 'two young otters who were fund abandoned after being orphaned.
'They're now doing well at this rescue centre in Broadford, 'run by husband and wife team, Paul and Gracie Yoxon.'
Wow!
What's their history, how did they end up here?
Well, Tay obviously came from the River Tay and Pebbles came from near Peebles.
It's always better to bring two otter cubs up together cos they do normal otter behaviour - they'll squabble over a fish and they'll learn to be otters as a pose to being tame.
It's a long-term commitment to look after an otter cub.
Cos they don't go back to the wild until they're about 12-15 months - that's the age they'd leave their mothers.
'Here on Skye, the otter population is healthy and numbers are up.
'But spotting them takes patience and an expert eye.'
All right, let's see how Grace is getting on.
We've got one on the shore just down there.
See that little dip in there?
Oh, look, there it is just up on the shore.
It looks like it's just hidden in that bladderweed, I think.
Yep, I think so.
It's disappeared.
I'm guessing it's gone in the water, but which way, I don't know.
'They're incredibly tricky to spot, but luckily for us, 'this little fellow was happily feeding close to shore.'
Look at that, that's fantastic.
Skye really has a way of captivating its visitors with its enormous landscapes, it's acres of sky and its wildlife.
It's a place that combines adventure with tranquillity but above all, it's a place to take in very, very slowly.
Still to come on Countryfile, the new students making their mark at the Royal Agricultural College in Cirencester.
And Charlotte sets sail in search of herring.
Now the credit crunch is meaning that many people are having to make quite a few cutbacks.
But some sacrifices are harder to make than others, as some horse owners are realising.
Here's Juliet.
'This is former racehorse, Kelroy Scarlet Buccaneer, 'or Bucks for short.
His owner's had him for the past 17 years, 'ever since he retired from racing.
'This morning is a momentous day in his life.'
But though he doesn't know it, Bucks' life is about to change because his owner just can't afford to keep him any more.
In a few minutes' time, he'll be led into a horsebox for the short journey to his new home.
.. Come here.
Do you think Bucks knows something's up?
Yeah, totally.
He's lively!
This morning - he normally comes to call - he didn't want his dinner and he's pacing up and down so yes, I think he definitely knows there's something going on.
But why have you decided to let Bucks go now?
When I had my daughter four years ago, it became very expensive then, and I think also the credit crunch.
I had to reapply for my job, my husband, unfortunately, his company downsized and he lost his job.
So I think as all this comes together and the cost of living, yes, it certainly mounts up.
When I got him 17 years ago, I never imagined I'd been in a situation where I can't afford to keep him.
I pay £30 a month insurance for him - luckily, because a while ago, he punctured his knee and the bill came to £3,600.
So if he wasn't insured, heavens knows how we would have paid for that.
Bucks, it's your final few minutes in your home.
What do you make of that?
Yeah...
He looks...
He looks ready to go!
He looks ready to go or he looks stressed, I'm not sure which.
Yeah, he is a little bit, actually.
He knows something's up, doesn't he, he really does.
'Ayse has given Bucks to the Horse Trust, 'a charity which runs a rest home for horses in the Chiltern Hills.
'It was set up by the Victorians to look after 'former working horses from London and now caters 'for the retirement needs of over 100 horses, donkeys and ponies.
'Bucks will be kept in isolation for a few weeks 'before he can join the other animals.
On arrival, 'the Trust's vet, Paul Jepson, carries out a series of tests 'to check for various diseases.
These include taking a swab.'
Oh, dear me!
Oh, dear!
Oh, good lad!
What a good boy, what a good horse.
So the idea of what we're doing, putting the swab up there into his throat cos if there is infection there, it will pick it up from the back of his throat.
That's all we need to do.
Fantastic.
Good boy - perhaps we can find you a carrot cos that was...
'Bucks is one of the lucky ones - 'rehomed at the Horse Trust by his devoted owner 'where he'll be very well looked after.
'But the Trust is full to capacity.
'Other horses during the coming winter months 'may no be so fortunate.'
Suddenly, the phone was ringing off the hook.
All with horse calls, desperate horse owners in desperate situation, and we began to realise that this has to be for a particular reason this is happening and we assumed and put two and two together - cos most of them were for financial reasons cos of the economic climate.
What do people do that literally cannot afford to keep their horses any longer?
We look at ways that maybe they can reduce the costs.
Horses come with lots of different needs, including farrier and dentistry and vet care, they need to be housed and fed.
But there are ways that we can maybe advise to reduce those costs so we can keep horse and owner together cos ideally, that is the perfect scenario - we want to keep horse and owner together for both their sakes.
Maybe consider some sort of rehoming scheme where people maybe have some land, they'd like to take in a horse.
We can maybe look at those schemes.
But sometimes, we have to address euthanasia, unfortunately, and that is a hard bridge to cross.
'National horse charities are familiar with 'the perennial problem of owners under-estimating 'the cost of looking after their animal.
'Keeping a horse at a livery stable can cost around £250 a week.'
What advice can you give in order to try and minimise those costs?
The first piece of advice we'd give is, try to plan ahead.
One of the things we've seen is that that the horse market is slowing down and it's not as easy to sell horses on as it was.
So you can't wait until the last minute and think you'll be able to just sell the horse - that can't be guaranteed.
So planning ahead...
It's easier said that done, I realise, but if possible, putting a bit aside each week to cope with further down the line.
There are various different things that you can do.
One might be getting someone to share your horse - perhaps someone else who can't afford their own horse, but would be willing to split the costs of keeping yours with you.
That can be ideal but you do have to be very careful about who you choose to come in and do the sharing.
We always suggest you've got a written and signed agreement in place so everyone knows where they stand.
The high cost of keeping horses means that the price of buying them has come down.
In today's market, you could pick up a pony for as little as £50.
But horse charities have a clear message for those who might be tempted...
If you weren't willing to pay for a horse when they were at their premium, then now isn't the time to be looking at it.
Although the price of buying the horse is coming down, the cost of keeping it is going up.
Please, don't be tempted - defer your decision, think about it for the future maybe, but whilst things are tough, don't take on a horse.
And horses feature in the Countryfile Calendar for 2009, which we sell in aid of Children In Need.
So far, it's raised more than £200,000 and if you'd like to buy one, here's how you do it.
It costs £9 and a minimum of £4 from each sale will go to the BBC's Children In Need appeal.
You can order right now, either on our website... ..or by calling the order line on...
To order by post, send your name, address and cheque to...
Please make your cheques payable to BBC Countryfile Calendar, and don't forget to allow 14 days for delivery.
And if you'd like to buy one in time for Christmas, well, you'd better be quick!
Now, on Countryfile, we often report the challenges facing people who earn their living from the land.
Everything from dealing with animal diseases to red tape, but there are still plenty willing to take up the mantle.
And in the next few months, we're going to be following the fortunes of the latest intake of students at the Royal Agricultural College in Cirencester.
In the heart of the rolling Cotswolds is a place that's helped fashion the British countryside.
The Royal Agricultural College has 850 students on courses from land management and organic farming to equine studies.
This year 316 new students enrolled and when they're not working, there's plenty of time to relax.
So how will they get on?
Their college is known as the Royal Ag, the Oxbridge of the countryside, and the future of agriculture is in their hands.
It's open day and Duncan Howie is showing prospective students around the Victorian gothic tower.
We started taking students, started educating in 1845.
With the average age of British farmers these days being 58, colleges like this need to inspire young blood if the industry is to have a future.
Obviously, when you first turn up to the Royal Ag it is a very small agricultural, like most agricultural universities, small college, small campus.
Probably many people would consider it to be quite quaint, but that's one of the main advantages of it, you get to know people, everyone that's there.
First year Jemima Showering is specialising in organic farming, a passion she developed back home in Berkshire.
Come on, turks.
Come on!
I'm feeding them at the moment some spaghetti left over from spaghetti Bolognese last night and they rather enjoy any form of scraps, be it spaghetti, baked beans, excess sweetcorn.
I started getting in to chickens when I was quite young and then when we moved up here we started with Buff, who's my old, my old trusty faithful cockerel.
And then it expanded quite dramatically.
I think at one time we had about 25, I think, all running around the garden.
But numbers get fewer the more you eat.
Being here I can have all my turkeys, I can have all my chickens, my pigs are just about to arrive, so I'll be able to have my pigs here, my dogs, I've got all the space in the world to do everything I've, sort of, ever wanted to do really with animals.
These are "Terracockers" - an accident... is what they'd be best described as I think.
This is mum.
This is their first encounter of being outside.
Mark Evans is a 37-year-old first-year agricultural student.
Recently made redundant from a car finance company in Newport, his dream is to set up his own smallholding.
I'm gonna do like a cauliflower cheese.
He's in student digs in Cirencester town centre.
There's 23 rooms, 17 are occupied at the moment.
And I think there's probably only about four of us from the UK.
So it's great, you know.
Well, I say four of us from the UK, it's myself - Welsh, obviously, and you've got Jeremy who's from Ireland, so there's only two English guys here.
This is a cheese sauce I made earlier.
One day Mark may be helping feed the nation.
But I want to do something different.
Er...
That was kind of forced upon me in the sense that my job was made redundant.
I worked in the finance industry, so I just want to do something a little bit more...
Do what I want to do, get out and about in the countryside and hopefully forge out a career there.
Back at college, Mark and Jemima are making their way to the first lecture of the day.
Oh, wow!
We've got mechanisation next, you do realise that, don't you?
I can handle that.
Oh, I'm not one for tractors, I'm afraid.
Well, you wouldn't be doing organic would you, with a plough and horse?
No, it's all about the digging, I reckon.
None of this tractor malarkey.
And as I said, you've got men to do that.
Oh, charming(!)
The college has three working farms in the surrounding countryside where the practical studying is done.
This is the first college farm.
Now, like all farms, it's evolved with time and we're left with a legacy of buildings around us here, that had functions in the past and have had to be adapted to other purposes in more recent times.
Nikolai will probably try and sell you a course on dry-stone walling here as we pass this by.
This is one of the skills along with tractor maintenance and welding and so on offered here.
Many of the students will also be placed on commercial farms to do hands-on work.
So far, it's been really great.
You know, learning all the different stuff that you sort of...
I thought that I was doing so much at home...
And there's so much more to do, and so much more to learn that you wouldn't even start to consider really.
I'm not from a farming background, so I just can't wait to get to the hands-on.
I wasn't really from a farming background, I started with some chickens and then progressed to some pigs and some turkeys and then more vegetables.
I suppose that's where my enthusiasm came.
And from wanting to know where my food came from.
And we hope to follow Jemima and Mark through their academic year.
I think there's not a better time to get into farming, actually.
Being from a non-farming background, it excites me.
It's such a diverse industry.
I hope to set up my own organic business when I finish, setting other people up, like I am at home.
And in two weeks' time we'll be back at the college to see an old tradition - the Christmas dinner.
And with plenty of young farming students to feed, the turkeys better be top of their class.
In the North Devon village of Clovelly, fishing for herring has been a way of life for more than 1,000 years.
But landing those Silver Darlings, as they're known, is becoming a bit of a challenge, as Charlotte has been discovering.
It's a lovely day here on the North Devon coast, but it is early, and frankly, I'm not a morning person.
But if you want kippers for breakfast, then first you need a herring, which is why I'm here looking for a fisherman.
They're harder to find than they used to be in Clovelly.
Now this village relies on tourism, but in the past fishing provided for nearly all the families here.
And at this time of year, that meant herring.
At the height of the herring trade in the 18th and 19th centuries, there were 100 herring boats based in this small port.
Today, there are two, owned by Steve Perham and his brother Tommy.
Today Steve's being helped by his future son-in-law, Ivan, and, of course, me.
They've already shot the drift nets, now all we have to do is find them.
At the beginning of the season when the fish are less, we live them in the water for three or four hours.
Right.
When the fish are getting thick, then an hour.
Sometimes even ten minutes, you'll catch enough fish.
Really?
How do you know where to put them in the first place?
They use the tides.
Whatever the tides are doing, use that.
And you're looking for where the fish are, you're looking for the coloured water.
That's what we're doing.
We didn't see coloured water, but after a mile of hard rowing, we finally saw the nets.
By which point poor Ivan was...indisposed.
You all right, Ivan?
IVAN RETCHES Ivan, you stay there.
You do my throwing up and I'll do your hauling in.
How much more net have we got to go?
Oh, quite a lot.
There's still hope.
Do you often get nothing at all?
Yeah, when the seal's around.
It's not that the seals are eating everything, it's they're scaring the fish off.
They scare it off.
A big thing like that in the water frightens the fish away.
They'll eat some of them, but they'll scare most away, and that's why we end up like this.
Which must be very frustrating.
That's the polite way of putting it.
Nearly 300 metres of nets and not a single fish and this in the middle of the herring season, which only runs from the end of September to Christmas.
Can you understand why other people are not coming in to this business?
Yeah, I can understand it.
Yeah, there's no future in it.
It is hard work.
And...
When the fish aren't there, the market isn't there, so there's no reason to come into it any more.
People just don't want the fish.
There are easier jobs for youngsters nowadays to do.
It wasn't always like this.
These old salts remember when herring, the Silver Darlings, were plentiful.
So what was it like when you were all herring fishing out of Clovelly here?
A lot better than what it was today.
I've seen 40, 50 boats here taking herrings.
And standing knee-deep in them.
Yeah, so we count the herrings here.
Herrings were sold as a maze, a maze of herrings - 600 fish.
And any boat crew, well, we used to catch ten dozen maze a night.
Now, what sort of boats are we talking about?
We're leaning on a boat.
Is this the kind you'd have been on?
No.
That one.
With the sails.
Picarooner got the nickname of the robber of the sea, because the big boats were in the harbour waiting for the tide to come in, where they could be launched out, and they would be gone, out there on top of the herring's shoals and then they could get into shallower water before the big boats could get in and they were first at the market.
Pirate boats they were, pirate boats, they called them.
You're latter-day pirates then, really?
Well, you could call us that.
Compared to the living of these two guys, what's it like herring fishing now?
Rubbish.
You cannot make a living with fishing.
I don't want to go into politics, but we've been sold down the river.
Fishing might be all but gone, but its heritage can be celebrated.
Clovelly's second herring festival aims to bring people into the village to eat, enjoy and spend.
Here's some herring.
And this is Steve's brother, Tommy.
How come you caught something Cos I'm better.
Simple as that.
No, it's just bad luck.
Sometimes the fish play in the night, middle of day, morning, sometimes in daylight, sometimes just in the dark.
It's just bad luck.
You went out yesterday and you caught loads.
Last evening it was, and I had three times this much, this amount, and that was in half an hour.
The day before I was out for five hours, only caught one fish.
It's just the way it goes.
There's no logic to this.
Not at all.
There are plenty of people.
Brilliant.
Doing me the world of good and Clovelly the world of good.
We don't tend to eat a lot of herring any more, but if anyone can change that, it's this man - historian and herring aficionado Mike Smylie is better known as the Kipperman.
Herrings used to be really important, didn't they?
Not just to Clovelly.
Vastly important.
In parts of the country they say employed a quarter of the population, one in four people was involved in the herring industry.
You've got to build the boats first, go out and catch them, make the nets, you've got to make the barrels, you've got the gutting lasses...
So what changed?
People's attitudes to eating the fish.
And then we've got over-fishing.
And the fish disappeared.
But herring is notoriously fickle.
It'll come year after year to the same spawning grounds and then the next year it will disappear, go somewhere else.
Is herring making a comeback?
It's making a brief comeback.
I don't think stocks are too fantastic.
One of the biggest problems are most of what is being caught is going for processing.
At times it's being used to feed farmed salmon.
That's what it's processed into, into fish food?
Yeah.
The oil is taken out to use in the supplement industry.
So instead of eating a good old healthy kipper or...to get the oil, you pop a pill and eat a bit of horrible farmed salmon.
Let's not pop a pill, let's go and get a kipper.
There is a fantastic smell here.
Do you want to open it up?
It's a very bizarre-looking thing, I have to say.
Oh, man!
It's a...
I call it my IKEA smoke house.
You take this all round the country?
Yes.
It comes apart.
Flat packs.
How many kippers have you got in there?
There's 40 in there at the moment.
There was 160 when I started.
Can I taste one?
I'll look for a nice one.
There's a nice one.
Get him off his tenterhooks.
I'll shut this up...
Shut this door.
..Otherwise this queue will riot.
Not only that, we'll be smoked out.
You want to taste one.
I'll get the bone out.
People say, "Kippers, ah, it's got a bone in."
They are fiddly to eat.
All you do is just get that and pull it out.
And there's the bone gone.
And it's just full of omega-3.
Not only good for your heart, good for your... good for your eyes, your brain... your joints.
So, in fact, although you may think I'm acting like a pig, I'm doing it cost it's good for me.
Thank you very much indeed.
Thank you.
I wasn't alone.
People queued and ate and queued and ate some more.
Fried herring, kippered herring, soused herring.
But to keep Clovelly's last two herring men in business, we'll have to eat a whole heap more.
In a few minutes' time, we'll be up there, following the Coniston mountain rescue team as they go to the help of someone in trouble on the fells.
And guess who it's going to be.
But, before that, over to London to get the Countryfile weather forecast for the week ahead.
The uplands of Britain are wild, magnificent and potentially very dangerous.
Conditions can change in an instant and it's not just inexperienced climbers and walkers who can find themselves in peril.
Even the most experienced can get caught out.
Just a few weeks ago, here in the Lake District, hundreds of people set out on a marathon in the mountains.
Many knew this landscape like the back of their hands but as the weather worsened the organisers were forced to call the event off.
Fourteen people had to be brought to safety, a reminder of just how vital the Mountain Rescue Service really is.
To keep on tiptop form, all mountain rescue teams have regular exercises.
Today, I've volunteered to be the victim for the Coniston one.
So here I am, high on the fells, miles from anywhere.
Luckily, I've got my OS map with me, so I can work out my position pretty quickly and then I need to get on the mobile phone and phone, not the Mountain Rescue Service, but the police.
999.
If this was a real emergency, my call would be forwarded by the police to the headquarters of the Coniston team.
Coniston rescue base.
The only information my rescuers have is that I'm on my own, and I've got some kind of leg injury.
It takes around half an hour to assemble the team.
It really is getting very cold now, but luckily I did bring a flask of coffee with me, so I can warm the cockles a little bit.
OK, we need radios.
Get the first-aid kit.
I'll get the radios.
If I hadn't had that reassuring message to say that they were on their way, I'd be getting really worried now because panic would have set in, I think.
With a potential stretcher case like me, it needs at least eight team members to carry the casualty down and two off-road vehicles.
They're both equipped as ambulances.
It just reinforces to me how important it is to have a map with you and to have a mobile phone, cos luckily there's a good signal around here.
We're still waiting for them.
If this was real, I'd be getting pretty scared by now, I'm sure, but...they won't be long and I've had my coffee, so I've also got with me a drop of sloe gin.
Never without it, it's great stuff on a cold day and, boy, do I need it now.
The team gets as far as it can with the vehicles.
Then it's all legwork, carrying a lot of heavy kit.
I'm keeping my eyes peeled.
They should be coming up from down that way.
I've just seen a bunch of people coming round the corner there, down in the valley.
It might just be a group of walkers, which would be great news anyway,.